Guide to the Kathleen Brady Papers on Ida Tarbell, 1976-1990 SC.1992.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Kathleen Brady Papers on Ida Tarbell
1976-1990
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Brady, Kathleen
SC.1992.01
10 Linear Feet (23 document boxes)
Ida Tarbell was a pioneering investigative journalist from Western Pennsylvania and who gained fame for her 1904 expose of Standard Oil. This collection consists of manuscripts and research materials that her biographer, Kathleen Brady, accumulated over the course of writing a book about Tarbell during the early 1980s.
Previous Citation
Kathleen Brady Papers on Ida Tarbell, 1976-1990, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Acquisition Information
Gift of Kathleen Brady on April 15, 1992.
Biography
Kathleen Brady is the author of Ida Tarbell: Portrait of a Muckraker, published in 1984 by Seaview/Putnam and again in 1989 by the University of Pittsburgh Press. Tarbell (1857-1944) was born in Erie County, Pa., and graduated from Allegheny College in 1880. She is considered by some to be the first investigative reporter. She wrote biographies of Napoleon Bonaparte and Abraham Lincoln, but is best known for her exposé, History of the Standard Oil Company, published in 1904.
Scope and Content Notes
Originally received in six archival storage cartons, the collection contains articles, photographs, and notes used by Kathleen Brady in her research on the book; manuscripts of the book; correspondence between the author and publishers; book reviews; and permission and grant requests. Brady's research began in approximately 1980 and she completed her book in 1983.
Related Material
The Ida M. Tarbell Collection, Pelletier Library, Allegheny College
Ida M. Tarbell Collection, Drake Well Museum Library
Ida M. Tarbell Papers, MSS413, Ohio University, Athens, Ohio
Arrangement
The collection retains its original order, with a very small number of item refiled to better reflect their intellectual content. It has been divided into the following series:
Series I. Brady's Manuscripts, 1980-1983
Series II. Publication of Biography, 1982-1985
Series III. Research on Ida Tarbell, 1976-1990
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Personal papers; Women journalists; Investigative reporting; Journalists -- United States -- Biography; Tarbell, Ida M. (Ida Minerva); Standard Oil Company
- Brady's Manuscripts, 1980-1983; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series consists of drafts and edited versions of Kathleen Brady's working manuscript for Ida Tarbell: Portrait of a Muckraker. Many are pasted together and/or heavily annotated.
  - Part II - Edited, Part 1, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Part II - Edited, Part 2, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Part II - Typescript - Original, Part 1, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Part II - Typescript - Original, Part 2, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript - IV, Part 1, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Manuscript - IV, Part 2, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript IV, Index Cards, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Parts I: Duty, Typescript, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Parts II: Exaltation - Typescript, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Part II: Success (D.C) - Typed Manuscript and Copy, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Part I: Duty - Chapters 1-3, 1980-1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Part II: Exaltation, 1980-1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Part III: Success, 1980-1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Chapter 7, 1980-1983 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Part III, Drafts and Notes, 1980-1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Chapters 11 and 12: Work Horse and At Rest, Drafts, 1980-1983 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Paris, 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Paris Manuscript, 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Chapter 8, Manuscript and Copy (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Pre-Standard Oil Manuscript - Part III: Success, 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Chapter 9, 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Chapter 10, 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Chapters 11 and 12, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Part I - Roughs, 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Standard Oil: Manuscripts, Part 1, 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Standard Oil: Manuscripts, Part 2, 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Chapter 7: The Lady of Muckrake, 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Publication of Biography, 1979-1989; II.
  The items in this series document the logistical process of publishing Brady's biography of Tarbell. This includes such materials as correspondence with publishers, permissions paperwork, and publicity materials such as press inquiries and reviews.
  - TV/Movie Sales, 1984-1986 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Author Questionnaire, 1979-1989 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Times Query Responses, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Author Correspondence, 1979-1982 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Permission to Publish Requests, 1980-1984 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Photograph Requests and Book Advertising, 1981-1989 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Washington Journalism Review, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Grants - Part 1, 1980-1987 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Grants - Part II, 1980-1985 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Proposal of Biography of Ida M. Tarbell, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Titusville Hist. Project, 1982-1984 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript - Part 1, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Larry's Edit - Part 1 and Part II (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Larry's Edit - Part II: Success (Later Part III) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Larry's Edit - Chapter 7 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Bibliography of Ida Tarbell, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Bound Galleys: Correspondence - Book Review Requests, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Research on Ida Tarbell, 1976-1990; III.
  This largest of the three series consists of Brady's notes and source materials for the Tarbell biography, remaining in Brady's original arrangement by subject and mostly with her original folder headings. Many folders contain photocopies of archival materials that Brady consulted at various repositories. She often labeled those research folders with the dates of the original manuscripts. In those cases, the dates became part of the folder title and were put in quotation marks. Also included are notes, scraps of draft materials, and a large number of index cards that Brady used during the course of her research.
  - Women's Studies, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Unused Tarbell Correspondence, 1904-1909 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Index Cards - Part I, 1980-1983 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Index Cards - Part II, 1980-1983 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Misc. Research - Esp. on Chautauqua, Childhood, Oil in PA, 1980-1983 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Poland (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - William A. White, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Unused (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Research on "Washington 1894-", 1980 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - William Tarbell, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - F.S. Tarbell, 1982-1984 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Ella Tarbell Price, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Research "1940s", 1941-1942, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Research "1930s - Part I" (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Research "1930s - Part II" (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Research "1920s - Part I", 1982 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Research "1920s - Part II" (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Research "1910s", 1981 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Research "1905" (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Research "1904" (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Research "1900s", 1980-1981 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Research "1901", 1990 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Research "1902" (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Research "1903 - Part I" (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Research "1903 - Part II" (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - My Book (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Standard Oil, 1980-1981 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Additions - Part I (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Additions - Part II (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Additions - Part III (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Archive Correspondence - Part I, 1979-1983 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Archive Correspondence - Part II, 1980-1983 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Archive Correspondence - Part III, 1980-1983 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - McCormick - Part I, 1980-1981 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - McCormick - Part II, 1976-1981 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Mussolini - Part I, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Mussolini - Part II (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - National Voter's League, 1913-1918 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Paris, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Nationalization of American Business (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Old Age (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Parkinson's Disease, 1980-1981 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Phillips (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Post Standard Oil, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Rockefeller, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Roseboro (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Seignobos-Mariller, 1896 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Teapot Dome - Part I, 1977-1984 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Teapot Dome - Part II (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Suffrage, 1911-1912 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Red Cross - Tarbell, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Red Cross Magazine, 1919-1947 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Rices, 1906-1942 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Article from the New Yorker, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Tariff (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - World War I/Women's Committee on the Council of National Defense, 1918 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Woodrow Wilson, 1922 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Washington - 90s - Used - Part I (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Washington - 90s - Used - Part II (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Standard Oil - Unused - Part I (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Standard Oil - Unused - Part II (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Loose Index Cards (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Jane Addams, 1981 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - The American - Used, Unused (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Chester H. Rowell and Ida Tarbell Interview, 1981 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Bethel Farm, 1983 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Tarbell Lectures on Biographies, 1931 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - John Burroughs, 1982-1987 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Chautauquan Years - Novel By Tarbell (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - The Chautauquan (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Giddens/Oil Fields Of Pennsylvania Book, 1903-1936 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Gary/Owen D. Young, 1925-1939 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Genealogy, 1981 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Diary (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Illness - Clifton Springs, 1981-1982 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Industrialism (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Book Introduction (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Henry James (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Labor Conference (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Lecture Circuit (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Life After 80 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Lincoln/Carl Sandburg Correspondence (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - H.D. Lloyd - Standard Oil (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Lincoln - Civil War - Part I, 1980-1982 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Lincoln - Civil War - Part II, 1981-1983 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Mahaffy (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Elizabeth Marbury, 1982 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - McClure's - Part I (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - McClure's - Part II (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Articles - Reynolds, 1920s-1930s (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Arms Limitations Conference (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - American Magazine (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Allen Room (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Allegheny College (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - All In A Days Work (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Addresses & Photos (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Jane Addams (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - 1930s & 1940s (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - 1920s Chronology 30s (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - 1910s (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - 1900s (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - JD Rockefeller (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Jaccaci (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Industry (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Income (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Illness (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Genealogy (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Florida (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Film (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Dunne (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Description (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Deam (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Consumer's League (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Colorado Trip (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - Childhood (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - Chautauquan (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - Charles 'Downer' Hazen (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - Character/Personality/Views (Box 20, Folder 17)
  - Brady, A.C. (Box 20, Folder 18)
  - Albert Bayden (Box 20, Folder 19)
  - Boston Transcript (Box 20, Folder 20)
  - The Biz of Being a Woman (Box 20, Folder 21)
  - Biz History: Schlesinger (Box 20, Folder 22)
  - Birthdays (Box 20, Folder 23)
  - Biography (Box 20, Folder 24)
  - Bibliography (Box 20, Folder 25)
  - Nevins (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Napoleon (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Mugwumps (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Muckraking (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Montague (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - McCormick-Turson (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Samuel McClure/McC 1899/McC 1901/McC 1905/McC 1930s (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - McClures (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - McClures Split (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Madame Roland (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Love Life (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - "Lockhart" (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Lecture Circuit (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Knox College (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Kent (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - Kansas (Box 21, Folder 17)
  - Judge Gary (Box 21, Folder 18)
  - Franklin Tarbell (F.S. Tarbell) (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Esther Tarbell (Mother) (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Steffens (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Standard Oil (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Siddall (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Rising of the Tide (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Research on McAll Mission in France, 1981 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - John Reed (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Prohibition (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Politics (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Poland (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Persons (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Pen and Brush (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - Peace Ship (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - Paris Peace Conference (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - Paris (Box 22, Folder 16)
  - Old Age (Box 22, Folder 17)
  - Owen Young (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Work (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Women's Issues (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Woodrow Wilson (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Washington 1890s (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Lillian Ward (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Walker (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Various Press (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Trusts (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - TR (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Tariff (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Scott Tarbell (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Sarah Tarbell/ Aunt Hat (Box 23, Folder 13)